<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of Thomas Tregosse late minister of the Gospel at Milar and Mabe in Cornwal with his character, and some letters of his, not long before his death.</title>
            <author>Gale, Theophilus, 1628-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12185513</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12185513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 890:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of Thomas Tregosse late minister of the Gospel at Milar and Mabe in Cornwal with his character, and some letters of his, not long before his death.</title>
                  <author>Gale, Theophilus, 1628-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tregosse, Thomas, d. 1671.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55769:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55769:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF <hi>THOMAS TREGOSSE</hi> Late Miniſter of the Goſpel, At <hi>Milar</hi> and <hi>Mabe</hi> in <hi>Cornwal:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With his Character; and ſome Letters of his, not long before his Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55769:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55769:2"/>
            <head>THE LIFE and DEATH OF <hi>THOMAS TREGOS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe's</hi> Life, unto the time of his Converſion.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Lives</hi> of Virtuous and Heroick Spirits have been in all ages eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of great uſe and efficacy, for the promoting of the like diſpoſitions in thoſe, who are of more awakened and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Souls. For Man, of all Creatures being moſt under the power of <hi>Imitation,</hi> he is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally more moved by <hi>Examples</hi> than <hi>Precepts: Examples</hi> are Leſſons to the Eye, and Table<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherein the <hi>Theory</hi> is demonſtrated in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55769:3"/>
                  <hi>Practice.</hi> Things <hi>Intelligible,</hi> which are more obſcure in the <hi>Idea</hi> and notion, are rendred as it were <hi>ſenſible,</hi> and ſo more familiar and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable by examples; which give a kind of <hi>Body, Life,</hi> and <hi>Motion,</hi> to general Doctrines and Inſtructions. As the beams of the Sun gain force by Reflection, ſo do Doctrines and Precepts, reflected from the examples of holy men. Notions and Precepts give us only a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Idea</hi> of what we <hi>ought to do;</hi> But the Lives of holy men tell us what by grace we <hi>may do;</hi> and withal, they offer unto us efficacious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> for the provoking of us by an holy emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to our duty. Thence the poor Pagan adviſeth us,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Stob. Sec. <hi>3.</hi> de prud.</note> 
                  <hi>To ſet before us the faireſt Copy of Virtue, and then to imitate the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, with ſome other private conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, have induced me to commend to the world the enſuing ſtory of <hi>Thomas Tregoſſe,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel; who was born at St. <hi>Ives,</hi> near the Lands-end in <hi>Cornwal.</hi> The Family of <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> whereof he was a branch, was not without noble blood lodged in its veins Some conceive it to be more ancient than the <hi>Norman</hi> conqueſt, a relique of the old <hi>Britains,</hi> ſeated in thoſe parts; though the title ſeem to be of <hi>French</hi> notation. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55769:3"/>acquaints us, that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>John Tregoſſe</hi> a Baron; who, though he died without iſſue, yet <hi>Henry Tregoſſe</hi> ſate as a Baron in the Parliament held <hi>An.</hi> 35. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the I. And <hi>Robert de Tregoſſe</hi> was one of thoſe Lords that ſided with <hi>Simon Monfort</hi> Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> againſt K. <hi>Henry</hi> the third. As for the ruines of this Family, the principal cauſe thereof deſerves a particular remarque One Mr. <hi>Roſcadden</hi> going in Pilgrimage, his Wife had in his abſence a child, or more: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, at his return, <hi>John Tregoſſe</hi> adviſed him to ſettle his Eſtate on ſome Friend, for the uſe of his Wife and Children, leſt, after his death, the Heir at Common Law, ſhould turn his Wife and Children out of doors. Mr. <hi>Roſcadden</hi> embracing his advice, deſired him to accept of this truſt; which accordingly he did; but inſtead of a Deed in truſt, he made it abſolute to himſelf, and his Heirs. As ſoon as Mr. <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadden</hi> wad dead, the ſaid <hi>John Tregoſſe</hi> entred on the Lands, and turned his Wife and children out of doors; who for ſome time lay in a Hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and every morning went forth on the dunghil, there on their knees imprecating the vengeance of God on <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> and his Heirs. After this time the Judgements of God ſignally appeared againſt this Family; <hi>Walter</hi> his Son, falling from his horſe in a fair way, broke his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55769:4"/>neck; others of his iſſue came to an untimely death; and a curſe hath remained on the eſtate ever ſince. This, Mr. <hi>Thomas Tregoſse,</hi> (whoſe Life we now relate,) was ſo greatly ſenſible of, as that it coſt him many Prayers for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of this curſe, as he himſelf aſſured me.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the Judgements of God on this Family; yet the Parents of Mr. <hi>Thomas Tregoſse</hi> were godly, and reputed among the number of the old Puritans. This was much ſeen in the pious education they gave this their Son, whoſe tender years they took care to have ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with the Principles of Religion and good Literature. At firſt his capacity ſeemed dull, till about the age of ſeven years, or after, his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence gave ſome notices of a quick apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tenacious memory. Indeed, he had from his youth a natural inclination to the work of the Miniſtry, and would oft, (when but a child,) mount up a ſtool or bench, and there, in his manner, preach to his companions.</p>
               <p>When he had attained a competent meaſure of Grammar Learning, he was ſent to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and placed in <hi>Exeter Colledge,</hi> under the Tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mr. <hi>Francis Howel,</hi> then Fellow of the ſaid Colledge; who perceived in him an awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened Spirit full of Vivacity and Intention, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he made good the character which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> gives of a young man, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55769:4"/>act vigorouſly,</hi> in what ever exerciſes he was engaged in. He did not, (as too many) abuſe the expectations of his Friends, by ſquandring away thoſe precious opportunities, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements vouchſafed him, for the elevating his natural capacity, by the acquirement of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Arts, and Philoſophick Sciences, wherein he made a good progreſs. Neither was he without a good intereſt in the eſteem of pious perſons, as it appears by the admittance which Reverend Dr. <hi>Conant</hi> gave him, as a Member into his Church. Alſo whiles he continued in <hi>Oxon,</hi> he began to feel ſome wounds of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. One day hearing Dr. <hi>Conant</hi> on <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4. <hi>O</hi> Ephraim, <hi>what ſhall I do to thee?</hi> &amp;c. Some paſſages of that Sermon made ſo deep impreſſion on him, as that his conſcience was filled with no ſmall terrour; when he went to his bed, he was not without fears he ſhould never ſee day; when in his ſtudy, that he ſhould never come out alive. So long as theſe awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing terrours of Conſcience, and ſick nights for ſin continued, he could not endure to hear a vain word, or to behold what had but the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſin. But theſe <hi>lights</hi> and <hi>heats</hi> of Conſcience did by degrees die away; Neither did they at that time determine in a thorow Converſion, as it will hereafter appear, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55769:5"/>
               <p>Having ſpent ſome time in the Univerſity, he returned to S. <hi>Ives,</hi> the place of his Nativity; where, having made ſome tryal of his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial gifts, the Inhabitants invited him to be their Miniſter. This he at firſt modeſtly refus'd; but being at laſt overcome by their importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, he agreed to ſpend ſome time among them; Whereupon he was <hi>Aug.</hi> 17. 1657, in that Church, ſet apart for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. He continued there two years a cloſe Student all the week, and conſtant Preacher twice every Lords day. Before his departure from this place, he took to him for Wife <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Sparnan,</hi> who proved a gracious, meek, humble, affectionate, and meet help to him. Whilſt he continued in this Town, there were two accidents, which deſerve a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque; The firſt was this; The Summer after his ſitting down among them, much of the fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeaſon was expired, and no <hi>Pilchards</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; the ſence whereof greatly afflicted their Spirits; that Town depending much upon the <hi>Pilchard</hi> trade. Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> adviſed them to joyn in a day of Prayer and Humiliation: which being performed, the next day appeared a great ſhole of Fiſh, whereof a conſiderable quantity of them were taken. The other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent which deſerves a particular remarque was this; the next Summer, the Fiſher-men,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55769:5"/>taking a great number of Pilchards on a Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, all that night was ſpent in ſaving of them; and the <hi>Seamen</hi> were very intent in drying their Nets the Lords day. This Mr. <hi>Tregroſſe</hi> rebuked them for; withal, giving them to underſtand, that they provoked the Lord deſervedly to withdraw his bleſſings from them, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened accordingly: For from that time, to the end of the Fiſhing ſeaſon, they had not another opportunity of imploying their Nets.</p>
               <p>He removed hence, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1659. to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carage of <hi>Milar</hi> and <hi>Mabe;</hi> where he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued his conſtant courſe of ſtudy, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; till he was ſilenced by the Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1662. Being prohibited the publick place of preaching, he ceaſed not to preach in his own Family twice every Lords day. Which being known in the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, divers, who had taſted of his Miniſtry in publick, could not but deſire to partake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in private. This being divulg'd, notice was given thereof to the Lord Lieutenant; who, upon his refuſal to take the Oath appointed for the <hi>Militia,</hi> committed him to the cuſtody of the <hi>Mareſchal,</hi> where he continued obout three Months ſpace; not ceaſing to preach to his fellow priſoners, beſides others who came to hear him: but at laſt he was releaſed by order from the Deputy Lieutenants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55769:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi>'s Converſion; and ſeveral Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that attended the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEptember</hi> 1663. Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> removed his habitation to the Baron of <hi>Kigilliack,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Badock,</hi> near <hi>Penryn;</hi> where he kept up his Lords days meetings, many flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him. About the begining of <hi>October</hi> 1664. he and his Wife lying awake in their bed, they felt a great Earth-quake, which made the room to tremble and quake under them, as they aphrehended: and that which gave them the greater cauſe of admiration, was, that no one elſe felt the ſame. But this was but a <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick</hi> and ſymbolick Image of that dreadful Tremblement or Earth-quake, which not long after Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> felt in his Conſcience. For, on the firſt of <hi>January</hi> following, it being the Lords-day, the Lord led him to preach on that Text, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47. <hi>And that Servant which knew his Lords will, and prepared not himſelf, neither did according to his will, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> On which he ſhewed, <hi>what a dangerous ſin it is to ſin againſt knowledge.</hi> The duties of the day being finiſhed, his old ſins were livelily preſented to him; eſpecially one among the reſt. Hereupon he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55769:6"/>to his Duties, but drove on very heavily; yet the Lord, by an omnipotent pull, drew him on. In one one Duty among the reſt, he was aſſaulted with that Scripture, <hi>Heb</hi> 12.17. <hi>For ye know, how that afterward, when he would have inherited the bleſſing, he was rejected: For he found no place for repentance, though he ſought it carefully with tears.</hi> He frequently aſſayed to ſhake off the chains and cords of the Spirit, grieving that he was bound up from the world; his performance of duties was not without much deadneſs and unbelief. But the Lord bound him faſt to his work, forcing him to follow on in a way of ſeeking. Sometimes he feared God would leave him to run into his former courſes; yea, that he ſhould not perſevere to the end of one day. But the Lord magnifyed his power and grace above and beyond his fears. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in reading, the Lord would ſet home threatning, then comforting Scriptures to keep him equally ballanced between hopes, that he might not ſink, and fears that he might nor preſume. He was detained for about 5 weeks ſpace under much bondage, and afflictive ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, with little or no diſcoveries of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious diſpoſition; till about the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> being under a reſolution to reveal ſome ſins which burdened his Conſcience, he met with a paſſage in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divine, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55769:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>greatneſs and freeneſs of Chriſts love and purchaſe;</hi> which, the Lord ſetting home, he was a little quieted and refreſhed by. The next day being the Lords-day, he had a ſweet heart-melting conſideration of his ſins, together with a lively contemplation of Chriſt pierced; to whom he directed an eye of Faith. And now he, who thought it an hard matter to ſhed one tear, drops many; the Spirit of the Lord alſo bringing to his heart that promiſe, <hi>I will pardon their iniquity, and remember their ſin no more:</hi> and that of Chriſt to <hi>Thomas,</hi> Jo. 20.27. <hi>Reach hither thy finger, and behold mine hands, and reach hither thine hand, and thruſt it into my ſide; and be not faithleſs, but believing;</hi> and this was promoted by reading the hiſtory of Chriſts Paſſion. Yet was he not without ſome doubtings ſtill; yea, at times, all theſe his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements ſignifyed no more than nothing. After this, he was carryed on in Duties, with more enlargement, and affectionate workings, eſpecially at times.</p>
               <p>And from this time he dated his converſion; For, albeit his converſion, for ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time before, was irreproachable, and his labours in the work of the Miniſtry indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable; yea, and his Zeal for Non conformity remarkable; yet he judged the whole of his foregoing life zeal, and labour in the Miniſtry,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55769:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be no other then a continued <hi>ſeries</hi> of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality and hypocriſie. And becauſe ſome of his friends who knew his former converſation well, could not but conceive that he had ſincere Grace, before this great turn; A friend of his diſcourſing with him on this point, he perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily affirmed, <hi>That he aſsuredly knew, that he had nothing of ſincerity before this great work,</hi> and withall he bewailed the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in that generally men were made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters before they were made Chriſtians; Yea, he was not without great fears, that many, who in humane eſtimation, now paſs for able and good Miniſters, will one day be found to be, according to Divine eſtimation, not ſo much as good or ſincere Chriſtians. Theſe fears, we may preſume, he grounded on his own experience of himſelf, (beſides other common obſervations,) who had the vogue of being a faithful Miniſter, before he was a faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. And that which yet adds further weight is this, that though he was before this time a conſtant and faithful Preacher, yet he could not ſay the Lord had given him any Covenant, as the fruit of his Miniſtry, though he received many Seals thereof afterward.</p>
               <p>Some ſhort while after theſe great, which he ſtrongly concluded were the firſt ſincere turnings of his Soul to God, being brought
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55769:8"/>very low in his Body and Spirits, he conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his death was near: Then was that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture caſt in, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>I ſhall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.</hi> And being again under a return of ſtrong perſwaſions and fear that he ſhould die, looking into his Bible, there was preſented to his eye that Text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.5. <hi>There were they in great fear where no fear was;</hi> which diſpelled that perſwaſion: and not long after, by the uſe of means, with the bleſſing of God thereon, he gain'd ſtrength in order to his future ſervice. Some ſhort time after this, on a <hi>Saturday,</hi> being very weak in body, and under deſpair of recovery, he went up to his chamber as well as his feeble legs would carry him, and fell down on his knees to Prayer: whilſt he was on his knees, on a ſudden, as it ſeem'd, agreat meaſure of ſtrength was given in to him, even to his aſtoniſhment. Whereupon he attempted to ariſe and walk; which he did two or three turns about his chamber very ſtrongly. Then calling for his Wiſe, ſhe ſoon perceived his pale cheeks cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their wonted colour ond complexion; and now he, that not many moments before, thought himſelf at the brink of the grave, was enabled to perform the duties of the evening, and next Lords-day, with much vigour and ſtrength. Since theſe ſignal marks of Divine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55769:8"/>ſavour and aſſiſtance, afforded both to his Soul and body; he, with ſome other Chriſtians ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a monthly Faſt, to afflict themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, for their own, their Family, and National ſins. After theſe his firſt turns to God, he found a more then ordinary aſſiſtance in his ſtudies and work, the Lord caſting in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant matter, and affecting him therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The Account of Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi>'s Service and Sufferings, with the Providences of God that appeared for him.</head>
               <p>ON <hi>April</hi> 30. 1665. it being the Lords day, Mr. <hi>Tregoſse,</hi> whilſt in Prayer, was much diſtracted about his intended Preaching in publick; whereunto he ſeemed to be drawn by a very ſtrange, though manifeſt courſe of Providence, which he ſtrongly reſiſted, till he was forced to yield. He had been that week wondring what the Lord would do with him; He could not ſtudy as formerly, but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to read a practical diſcourſe of Self-denyal: The Lord furniſhed his contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with many paſſages about ſuffering; And the Creatures duty to <hi>be,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> in the <hi>will</hi> of his Creator, and at his diſpoſement. In the end
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55769:9"/>of his reading, caſting his eye on his Bible, the firſt thing he met with, was that, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.36. <hi>When he ſaw the multitude, he had compaſſion on them, becauſe they fainted, and were ſcatter-abroad, as ſheep having no ſhepherd.</hi> At the view of which Text, he inwardly trembled; and the Lord ſeemed immediately to intimate, that he ſhould put on like bowels. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he queſtioned within himſelf, where he ſhould finde ſuch an opportunity of publick Preaching? <hi>Mabe.</hi> (a Daughter-church to <hi>Milar,</hi> which hath Preaching onely every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lords-day) was preſented to his thoughts. After many Diſputes, being loth to yield to the will of God, he concluded to ſend thither, to know whether any Miniſter would be there the Lords-day following: anſwer was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there would be none. But doubting ſtill, whether he might look on this as a Call, he caſt his eye on his Bible, and fixed on that expreſſion. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.33. <hi>No man, when he hath lighted a Candle, putteth it in a ſecret place, or under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick, that they who come in may ſee the light.</hi> This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered all his objections, allayed all his carnal fears, and confirmed him in his reſolution of Preaching in publick the next Lords-day. When the Sabbath came, he went on, and found the People willing, and all things ſuiting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55769:9"/>with the opportunity: neither found he any diſturbance, but was much aſſiſted in all duties to the end.</p>
               <p>The rumor of this days work was ſpread abroad, and came to the ears of Mr. <hi>Thomas Robinſon,</hi> a Juſtice of the Peace. The next Lords-day, <hi>May</hi> 7. being rainy in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> preached in his own houſe, on <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. <hi>In your patience poſſeſs ye your Souls:</hi> without any expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſturbance that day, by reaſon of the weather. But after the Sermon was ended, Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> came to the dore, and after entrance, took the names of thoſe who were preſent; requiring Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> to give ſurety for the good behaviour, or to render himſelf to the Conſtable upon his order, the <hi>Monday</hi> ſevennight enſuing; Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to do the firſt, but promiſed the latter. After Mr. <hi>Robinſon's</hi> departure, they met again in the afternoon without any diſturbance. The next Lords-day he preached again at <hi>Mabe</hi> without interruption. But when the Exerciſes were finiſht, he was ſerved with a Warrant to appear before Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> at <hi>Helleſtone,</hi> on the <hi>Tueſday</hi> following. At his appearance he vindicated his preaching with much boldneſs: But after all, was ſent to <hi>Lanceſton-Goal,</hi> there to remain for three Months; to which he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55769:10"/>not only patiently, but joyfully. In his way to the Goal, he embraced all occaſions for the comforting thoſe chriſtian friends he met with. And whilſt he continued in Priſon, his Spirit was very free and enlarged under many gracious influences and refreſhments. His time there was ſpent in reading the Word, Holy Meditations, Faſting, Prayer, Holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with, and preaching to thoſe who were his fellow Priſoners, and Viſitors. Few came to viſit him, but did, or might gain by conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with him. The time of his Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being expired, <hi>July</hi> 29. he came out of Priſon; and after his return home, took the firſt convenient opportunity to keep a day of Thankſgiving, for the many experiences of Gods goodneſs towards him, and his, during his confinement.</p>
               <p>He had not been at home above four days, before Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> gave out, that he would ſpeedily ſend him back again to the place from whence he came: in order whereto, on <hi>Friday</hi> or <hi>Saturday</hi> after, he providing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ride to Market, there (as it is reported) to procure another Juſtice to joyn with him in a Warrant for a ſecond Conviction of Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> for a Conventieler, and to proſecute ſome others; whilſt he was at a Tenement of his, his own Bull (which was never known to hurt any before,)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55769:10"/>followed him in a Field, with much fury, and gave him deadly wounds, whereof he ſhortly dyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 20. being the Lords-day, Mr. <hi>Tregoſse</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t again and preached at <hi>Mabe</hi> Church, without any diſturbance; as alſo that day fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, ſpending the interval with much activity in his Maſters ſervice, elſewhere. He had many diſſuaſives from chriſtian friends againſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick preaching; but all arguments urged, could not ſatisfy his Conſcience. He was again ſent to <hi>Lanceſton</hi>-goal for publick Preaching; whither, <hi>Sept.</hi> 18. he went with comfortable perſuaſions, that God would be with, and care for him and his Family; which was fully made good. This ſecond Impriſonment conduced much, through the Lords benediction, to the good of many Souls: For the report of his bonds being ſpread far, divers came to viſit him, to whom he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Spiritual gifts; and there were ſome <hi>Oneſimus</hi>'s, whom he begat through the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, in his bonds. During this impriſonment, he took ſeveral opportunities of viſiting the Priſoners, labouring to convince them of their ſinful ſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo whilſt under this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, he enjoyed many <hi>Divine Suavities,</hi> and ſpiritual refreſhments in Duties; with many gracions returns of Prayer; and ſome prophetick intimations of future Providences;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55769:11"/>As, <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. he praying for opportunities of ſervice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After the Duty was ended, he firmly believed he ſhould be releaſed of this reſtraint, and be no more impriſoned in that place; which proved true, notwithſtanding ſeveral attempts to the contrary. <hi>October</hi> 7. being much enlarged in praying for patience, and ſubmiſſion to the will of God; he grew very confident, that ſhortly God would farther try him. So <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. God ſeemed ſundry ways to intimate to him, that ſome great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction was near, but that he ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from it; all of which proved true, as it will be ſhewn. Again, <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. being earneſt in Prayer for the Nation, he was ſtrongly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to believe, that ſome great judgement was not far off. About which time, there was oft caſt into his thought that Scripture, <hi>Iſa</hi> 21.16. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord unto me, within a year, according to the years of an hireling, and all the glory of</hi> Kedar <hi>ſhall fall.</hi> He oft mentioned to ſome of his intimate friends, the ſtrong Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion this Scripture made on his thoughts; much wondring what it ſhould mean; but a little before the year expired, the Conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>London</hi> happened, which fully interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his former Impreſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decem.</hi> 14. he was delivered out of Priſon; and upon his return home, he kept a day of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55769:11"/>Thankſgiving, and ſhortly after he did ſet apart every <hi>Tueſday</hi> as a Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing or Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving day; which he kept either in private, or with his Family, or with others more pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Jan.</hi> 8th. being the Lords day, he went to <hi>Mabe,</hi> where he preached both parts of the day without interruption: which was attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this remarkable Providence, that whilſt he was there, the Conſtable, with an Officer from <hi>Pendennis</hi> Caſtle, came to his houſe, but miſſed of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 12. he began a journey towards the Eaſt of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and from thence into <hi>Devon:</hi> The Lords day, and the Wedneſday after his houſe was ſearched. In this journey he went forth on the South of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and returned on the North; exerciſing in all places where he came, and receiving great encouragements, as to the fruits of his labours. At his return <hi>Febr.</hi> 4th. going to preach at <hi>Mabe,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſerved him with a Warrant, to carry him under the Cuſtody of the <hi>Mareſchal,</hi> as a dangerous and ſeditious perſon: which indeed he was ſo far from being guilty of, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as medled in his preaching, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conferences, with the preſent Diſcipline or Liturgy of the Church; much leſs with matters of State: Nay, he perſwaded others to be obedient to the higher powers: and in his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55769:12"/>daily exerciſes he did put up many fervent pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions for the King. Being under the cuſtody of the Mareſchal at <hi>Bodmin,</hi> this impriſonment brought him to the acquaintance of ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who reaped much benefit by his Miniſtry. The Mareſchal was civil to him; yet he met with more difficulties then in his former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement; but the Lord honoured him with the converſion of ſeveral ſouls. He continued in this priſon till about the midſt of <hi>September</hi> 1667. Being at a certain time earneſt in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for enlargement, a Scripture was preſented to his thoughts which made ſo deep impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on him, as that he was filled with a great confidence, that if he were delivered, it would be by order from the Kings Majeſty. Not long after, whilſt he was under various affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, touching his Family, the Mareſchal received a ſpecial order from the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty for his enlargement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 1668. coming to <hi>Penryn</hi> to preach his <hi>Monday</hi>-Lecture, he fell ſick of a Fever, which held him all that week. On the Lords day mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the ſenſe of his own weakneſs did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what affect him; becauſe the people, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on his Miniſtry, had none to ſupply his place: Whereupon, he had that Scripture im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed on his thoughts, <hi>Eſa</hi> 40.31. <hi>They that wait on the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55769:12"/>This wrought ſo much upon him, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ariſe: All about him were very preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to divert his reſolution, knowing how exceeding weak he was; but they could not prevail: He having got on his cloaths, caſt himſelf on the Lords work. As he went on, ſtrength was gradually given in, ſo that he preached thrice that day, chooſing that Text before cited. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.31. for his ſubject; and, to the great admiration of himſelf and his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, was well at night; neither did he feel any reliques of his diſtemper afterward.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the year 1669, the number of the Auditors was ſo much augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as that the rooms they uſually met in, would not contain them; which occaſioned the removal of the Meeting into a large Barn; until being ſummoned by the Proprietor of that Barn to quit his hired Houſe, he took up his habitation in the Town of <hi>Penryn.</hi> Before his remove, a <hi>Mittimus</hi> came from the Seffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, grounded upon as information of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, to ſend him to the Goal at <hi>Lanceſton,</hi> for publick preaching: The Conſtables com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſerve the Warrant, one of them, more furious then his fellow, whilſt he reaſon'd with Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe,</hi> with the <hi>Mittimus</hi> in his hand, ſunk down in the place, for the preſent, as it were dead; but being, by the diligent endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55769:13"/>of thoſe who were preſent, brought to himſelf again, he departed without executing the Warrant. That which makes this the more remarkable, is, that this Conſtable was a ſtrong man, and never fainted in all his life before. And though they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me again ſome days after, to execute their Warrant, yet had they not power to carry him to Priſon; For which, as it was ſaid, the other Conſtable was fined the next Seſſions.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Lammas</hi> Aſſize, 1669. Mr <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome affairs which called him to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> he was invited to viſit ſome part of the <hi>North-weſt</hi> of <hi>Devon;</hi> whence, for preaching at a private houſe in the Pariſon of great <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,</hi> he was ſent to <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal, with ſeveral others of that Town, and <hi>Bideford;</hi> who being all Bailed, had for that time no other trouble, then to traverſe a Bill for Riot preferred againſt them. In his return from <hi>Exon,</hi> he ſpent ſome few dayes at <hi>Crediton,</hi> where he contracted an intimate friendſhip with a perſon, who was providentially caſt there at the ſame time; to whom he unboſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many of the choiceſt accidents of his life, and ſecrets of his heart: And albeit they never ſaw each other afterward, yet this friendſhip was preſerved inviolable, and improved by Paper-converſation, till death made a diſ-uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55769:13"/>or rather a preſent ſuſpenſion. This trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which befell Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> was the occaſion of much good to many ſouls in thoſe parts: for it opened a door to many hundreds in <hi>Devon,</hi> who reſorted to him in his Travels: and ſo became partakers of his Miniſterial gifts; which were very effectual through the concurrence of Divine Grace. This made him lay out himſelf day and night to the utmoſt, allowing his body no more then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme neceſſity required, that ſo he might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all advantages for the advance of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſervice. The Bill preferred againſt him at <hi>Exeter,</hi> neceſſitated him to attend the two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Aſſizes; where he was at laſt freed by Proclamation; but mean while, his return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe parts was of no ſmall advantage for the propagation of the Goſpel. Some of thoſe perſons who diſcovered their malice againſt Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe,</hi> for preaching at <hi>Torrington,</hi> were ſhortly taken away by unnatural deaths, not without ſignal marks of Gods diſpleaſure againſt them, as it appears by his following Letter, <hi>Sept.</hi> 16. 1670.</p>
               <p>Not long before his death, he was ſtrangely, he knew not how, taken up in converſing with the ſtate of departed Saints, martyred for the Teſtimony of Jeſus; as he himſelf acquaints you, in his following Letter to his friend, <hi>Octob.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55769:14"/>7th 1670. Which indeed was a prophetick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of the nearneſs of his Diſſolution, and entrance on that life which he was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately more fully to partake of. Which brings to my remembrance an old obſervation which I had from a great<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Padre Paul.</hi> Hiſtor. Trent.</note> Maſter of Wiſdom, <hi>That it is natural for men near their grave from ſome intrinſick cauſe, unknown to themſelves, to be diſtaſted with humane affairs,</hi> &amp;c. What this wiſe man obſerved of men in general, I think is moſt true of many holy Chriſtians, who a little before their diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are frequently called off, and ſeperated from humane affairs, to a fiducial converſe with coming <hi>Glories,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> of juſt men made perfect; which was the frame of Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe's</hi> Spirit, not long before his death; though he himſelf was not apprehenſive that his change was ſo near.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Mr <hi>Tregoſſe</hi>'s laſt Tryals, and dying Speech to his Friends.</head>
               <p>AFter Mr. <hi>Tregoſs</hi> came to reſide at <hi>Penryn,</hi> he hired a Houſe for a Meeting on the Lords day in the Pariſh of <hi>Mabe,</hi> where he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55769:14"/>exerciſed without interruption, from <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer</hi> 1669, to the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1670. After which day, there were two debauch'd perſons turned Informers, hoping thereby to get fuel for their luſts: who having obtained a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, required the Officers to attend them every Lords-day, and made oath againſt Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe,</hi> and others, for a breach of the Statute then in force againſt Conventicles. This ſacred away moſt of his Hearers, eſpecially thoſe who had any conſiderable Eſtates. Though there were divers Fines laid on him, which amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to 220 <hi>l.</hi> yet the Lord ſo ordered things, as nothing he had was ſeized upon. This Meeting being thus broken, he reſolved to drive the nail that would go, and to preach the oftner unto a Statute number: herein his labours were ſo many and great, as if his body were of Steel, he could not hold out long; He preached five times every Lords-day, and in the evening made repetition of ſome part; He alſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the Tueſday and Thurſday duties, beſides other Exerciſes. He was often adviſed by his friends to favour himſelf, and moderate his pains; but the great zeal he had for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, and advancing the work of God, did ſtop his ears againſt all diſſuſives of this kind. Having at laſt worn out himſelf, and exhauſted his Spirits, he fell into a griping of the Bowels,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55769:15"/>occaſioned by a <hi>Flatus hypochondriacus,</hi> (as his Phyſician affirmed) which brought him ſo weak, as his friends ſuſpected him to be paſt recovery, and he himſelf expreſſed a longing deſire to be diſſolved. But the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reprieve him a little longer, and put him once more upon his feet, though he took not the air. As ſoon as he perceived a ſmall recruit of ſtrength, he began to fall upon his work again; this continued but a very ſhort time, till a Fever ſeized on him, and in a few days did ſet and end to all his Labours and troubles. His his deportment during both his ſickneſſes, was like his life, very ſweet and heavenly. Upon the <hi>18th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> obſerving the hour of his diſſolution at hand he took his farewell of his friends in a long ſpeech, whereof you have a part, as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I though I ſhould have had ſome more turns with my Lord in his Gallery; but he hoth turned his back, and is gone, and calls me to come after him: Indeed, though I had ſome diſtemper of Body, yet I did not think death was ſo nigh, till putting my hand on my brow, I felt the tokens thereof. Think, think not therefore 'tis a fooliſh phantaſie that moves me to ſpeak; for I know it to be right reaſon. And ſeeing the Lord hath left with me a few mouthfuls of breath, Let me, who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55769:15"/>am your faithful Paſtor, at the taking my farewell of you, drop a few words among you, before he calls away this breath of mine, and ſay, breath no more through that body, but lay it in the duſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>O my friends! my friends! you know that I have often warned you of an evil day, and now I muſt once more tell you, that there is a dead day, a dark day coming. O! what will this poor people do? O my Friends, did we think, that after ſo many Faſting and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation days, after ſo many Thankſgiving days, after ſo many Sacrament days, we ſhould ſee ſuch a day as this? O, but it may be you will ask me this queſtion. Do you really believe that you ſhall dye? Indeed, friends, there is nothing but Omnipotence can bear me up. And if you ask me, what I think of my ſelf? Truly, friends, I can ſay that I have walked among you by the pure copy of the Holy Scriptures, and Life of Chriſt; and through the Grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus, I ſhall be preſented ſpotleſs to the Father. Indeed, when I was young, I had my youthful vanities; but in the year 1664 upon a New-years day, the Lord was pleaſed to meet with me, and then, even then, did he ſet all my ſins in order before me: And theoſe very ſins which were ſmall to me before, were by the Spirit of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55769:16"/>Lord in that Rod, made as bitter as death it ſelf. My ſleight childhood-ſins, my ſlender youthful ſins, were to me very hainous and abominable. Wherefore, my friends, I charge you to make a conſcience of thoſe ſins, yea, of the leaſt of them which I have warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you of.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Some may think me paſſionate, and ſome may think me ſevere and uncharitable; but now I repent that I had not dealt more plainly with you. However, in the truth of the Lord; according to mine ability, I have walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you; and I hope you will not think it tedious if I drop a few words upon my grave before I dy.</q> 
                  <hi>Then the Phyſician ſteeping to him, with an intent to deſire him to leave off ſpeaking, leſt he ſhould ſpend his ſpirits too much, M.</hi> Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſſe <hi>ſaid,</hi> 
                  <q>Give me leave to ſpeak, for I am upon the borders of eternity; and I think you all look upon me as a dying man, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may ſuffer me to ſpeak as much as I can.</q> 
                  <hi>Then he proceeded;</hi> 
                  <q>I am going to my great God, to my dear Father, to my beſt Friend; to him in whom I have believed: His face I hope to ſee, in his boſom I hope to lye down this day. Oh! what unſpeakable glory is it to ſee the glory of mine everlaſting God? O, my Friends! I muſt tell you the truth; though ſometimes there have been upon my phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55769:16"/>ſtrange black clouds, which made me to ſpeak ſomewhat inconſiſtent, and were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly blown off again; yet little doth any one know the reviving in-comes I had then, even then from my God. And the laſt Lords day at night, the Lord gave me ſweet turns with himſelf. Oh! it was a pleaſant night with me, I was up with God, and God was down with me. Oh! it was to me as the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Paradice. Oh! how ſweet was it to me? And now my friends, I muſt tell you, that through many tribulations you muſt enter into the Kingdom of God. Some of you have told me your thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, that I have walked in all good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Oh friends, whatſoever things ye have ſeen in me that were honeſt, whatſoever things were juſt, whatſoever things were pure, whatſoever things were lovely, whatſoever things were of good report, purſue thoſe things. Rely not upon the world, for the world will leave you could and helpleſs. And now friends, I muſt go to ſee the Lord, and this Body of mine muſt be laid in the duſt and never ariſe more, till the Reſurrection-day. And muſt many of you go from this place, and come naked before the face of God? (though I hope better of ſome of you.) Oh friends,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55769:17"/>if there be any hope, if there be any love, if there be any conſolation in you, think on theſe things; You know I have. When I came to this town, ſome may think my deſign in coming was to fill an empty bagg, and to get a livelihood amongſt this people; but God is my witneſs I had not this in my eye; I ſought not yours, but you. And now friends, fleſh and bloud will ſay; It is hard to part with dear friends, to part with a dear Wife, to part with dear Children. But as the Lord hath given them to me, ſo I now leave them with the Lord. And I call you to witneſs, that I leave this dear Wife of mine with the Lord, and my dear Children with the Lord, to be protected by him, to be maintained by him, to be kept blameleſs to the day of his appearance. Though Men may prove unkind to them; as I ſuppoſe they will, yet I know the Lord will not. I muſt into Eternity; the Prophets cannot live for ever; neither can they Propheſie for ever: I have been but a young branch, and you ſee the Lord is cutting me down this morning. O bleſſed Lord God? ſhall there not be a meeting in Paradice? ſhall not thy ſervant ſee thee, and love thee, ond be embraced by thee? O Lord give a good evidence to thy ſervant, that he may know that he belongeth to thee. Lord
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55769:17"/>thou haſt given him the working of an holy faith; and of an heart-purifying ſpirit: And are not theſe tokens of thy free grace, and of thine eternal love in Chriſt Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s? And now Lord God, thy ſervant muſt away and be about other work, thy ſervant muſt away to holy Angels; and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect: He muſt away to ſerve his Lord in the upper Chambers: He muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Lord, and never look on theſe earthy things more. And now, O friends, one thing I tell you, I ſhall come again with my Lord, in moſt excellent Glory; and you then muſt come before him: But I fear, I fear, that ſome of you will be found then to be in a very low, and poor, and miſerable condition. Well, I commend you to the love and grace of God, the Eternal Father, in Jeſus Chriſt. And I pray you to get your hearts full of love to God; and of the grace of God; and full of the holy Ghoſt. And now think on theſe things, that I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to you, in the name of the Lord. I muſt go, and deliver up my accounts to God: And on that I might deliver them up freely! that I may be able to ſay, <hi>I have run my race; I have finiſhed my courſe; I have fought the good fight; I have kept the faith; and what remains but that I receive the Crown, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55769:18"/>the Lord Jeſus, the righteous Judge, hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for me.</hi> And now I commit my ſelf to the Lord; and my Wife and Children to the Lord— <hi>I commit my ſpirit to thee, O Father of ſpirits;</hi> I commit my ſoul to thee O dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lord: Keep theſe that do believe on thee.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words he ſpake with a more audible and plain voice, than he was wont to do, in his ordinary Preaching: And about an hour and half after he had ended his ſpeech, he departed this life, <hi>Jan.</hi> 18. <hi>An.</hi> 1670.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V. Mr.</hi> Tregoſſe's Character.</head>
               <p>HAving given ſome ſtory of Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe's Life</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> it may be, not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Uſeful, to give ſome Character of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Converſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Tregoſſe</hi> was of a middle ſtature, his Hair black; his Face paliſh, not perfectly round,<note place="margin">His Natural capacity.</note> nor long. His <hi>Spirit</hi> was Maſculine, Generous, and Great; agreeable to the condition of his Anceſtors. There was a ſparkling <hi>Vivacity</hi> apparent in moſt of his intenſe Actions. His <hi>natural humour</hi> was not moroſs but affable: yet was he not without a tincture of darke
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55769:18"/>melancholy; which yet his grace improved to a great meaſure of ſeriouſneſs. He had alſo ſome ſparks of choller; which being ſpirited by warm affections for God, brake forth into a pure flame of Divine zeal. His natural <hi>Judgment</hi> ſeemed deep, and ſolid; his will firm and fixed; his memory tenacious and faithful; his Affections tender and active: And the whole capacity of his ſoul fit for great exploits.</p>
               <p>But the moſt Illuſtrious and bright part of his Character regardeth his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious capacity, and diſpoſitions.<note place="margin">His univerſal Holineſs.</note> His perſonal holineſs was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, even unto great viſibility: And, I think, few, in this age, have, for ſo ſhort ſtanding, made a larger proficience in the School, and ſervice of Chriſt. After <hi>Jan.</hi> 1664. (from whence he dated his converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) he baniſht from his heart, and life many vanities, he had been formerly adicted unto. Neither did he gain his godlineſs, at ſo cheap a rate as moſt profeſſors do: No; his heart was firſt deeply wounded for ſin, and thence delivered from it: He was, for ſome while, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many extremities, from a <hi>Spirit of Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> and theſe made way for a <hi>Spirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption.</hi> He was ſoundly convinced of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual death by ſin, and that opened to him a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55769:19"/>door of life by Chriſt. And, the entire change of his heart much appeared in the change of his life, and laſt end. Neither had ſome particular graces only a place in him; but a <hi>combination</hi> and <hi>complexion</hi> of many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable graces, ſeemingly oppoſite, ſeemed viſible in him. How <hi>affable</hi> and courteous was he; and yet how <hi>ſevere</hi> again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſin? What meekneſs and humility in his own cauſe? and yet what courage, and magnanimity in the cauſe of God, ſhone in him? How much holy fear, and ſelf-jealouſie; and yet how much Chriſtian boldneſs, and confidence was he poſſeſſed with? What an inflexible, and ſtrong bent of heart for God, againſt ſin, ſeemed he to have? and yet how flexible and complying with others, for their good was he?</p>
               <p>He did not, as ſome, take Chriſt to eaſe himſelf of his work; or to ſecure his luſts;<note place="margin">His Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</note> but to kill them and to quicken him to dutie. His peace of Conſcience was maintaned, not by peace, but war with Sin; it was not only from, but alſo in God. He had, not only form of Chriſt in his life, and Picture of him in his fancy; but alſo the Image of, Union with, and love for Chriſt in his heart. He affected not ſo much to entangle his thoughts in diſputes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55769:19"/>the controverſies of Religion; as to get the power of it ſtamped on his ſoul. His faith did not lye level with worldly Intereſt, but oppoſitie thereto. He climbed not, as ſome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the top of an high profeſſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing a deep foundation in ſelf-denial. He borrowed not, as to many, the Mask of Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on to conceal a rotten heart; but was unſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tisfied in his heart-inquiries after grace, till he arrived to ſuch a full meaſure thereof, as is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttainable by any hypocrite.</p>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yly progreſs in <hi>mortification</hi> of ſin, ſeemed very remarkable,<note place="margin">His morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous. He knew full well, that one reigning luſt would <hi>darken</hi> and <hi>harden</hi> his heart; yea, bring all into captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and therefore durſt not gratify any luſt, in the leaſt. He was content to give up his luſts to death for Chriſt, who gave up his ſoul to death for him: He thought it not much to part with a beloved ſin, for a beloved Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Yea, he ſeemed to take more pleaſure in ſubduing his unlawful deſires, then others do in the fulfilling of them And leſt his fleſh ſhould impoſe on his more noble part, he innured himſelf to many bodily ſeverities; and deprived himſelf of ſuch natural refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which others too much indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in. Yet did he not content himſelf with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55769:20"/>external mortification, but maintained a daily conflict with the whole body of ſin, in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, yea, he would oft blame himſelf much for ſpiritual ſins, as <hi>Infidelity; pride,</hi> &amp;c. Which others could leaſt blame him for.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Crucifixion</hi> to the world was not leſs viſible:<note place="margin">His Crucifixion to the world.</note> He ſeemed to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a great indifference of Spirit for things indifferent; to give periſhing things but periſhing affections. As our bleſſed Lord gave his Heaven for him, ſo he thought it not much to give his earth for his Lord: He could not part with Chriſt for any worldly good; and therefore was willing to part with all for Chriſt. The believing views he had of future Glories, darkned the world glories to him; ſo that he ſeemed to admire nothing, but approching glory, or what related thereto. Poverty in Chriſts way was greater riches to him, then a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate in the ways of ſin. He knew how to abound in his wants, by contentedly wanting what the Lord thought not fit for him, and thereby crucifying his deſires, he made the Croſs of Chriſt eaſy to him. His deſires were low, and therefore his ſpirit high above the frowns, and ſmiles of this lower world. He ſeemed better pleaſed in his mean condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55769:20"/>then worldlings are in the higheſt. His mind was too great, to put a great value on the <hi>nothings</hi> of this life: He brought his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural deſires into a narrow compaſs, and thence gained a great inlargement of Spirit.</p>
               <p>By his long ſufferings he gained a great <hi>dexterity</hi> and skill in bearing the Croſs: By ſtarving ſin,<note place="margin">His Art in bearing the Croſs.</note> and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying his heart to the world, he took out the ſtings of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. He knew, that the Divine will was more Eligible then his own; and therefore he endeavoured to conform unto it, as well by <hi>paſſive</hi> as <hi>active</hi> obedience. He knew he could not glorifie God more, then by being content, that Gods Glory ſhould gain by his private loſſes. He durſt not make ſin a ſhelter againſt ſufferings; or bear falſe witneſs againſt God, by repining under the Croſs. He was not ſo well pleaſed with ſin, as to prefer it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſufferings: Or ſo ill-pleaſed with ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as to fly from them when called thereto. He innured himſelf to the yoke of Chriſt, and ſo gained the Art of bearing his Croſs. His <hi>Conſcience</hi> continued under a lively ſenſe of ſin, and that made him dead, and in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſenſeleſs as to ſuffering. His <hi>Will</hi> was ſo far broken, as that it could chearfully bend, and ſubmit to the Croſs; yea, welcome croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55769:21"/>when in Gods way. When God brought him into any affliction or ſuffering, he waited there till God brought him out. He knew himſelf to be nothing, and that made him bear any thing from God, with contentment: And by knowing his own vileneſs, he learnt to juſtify God in every croſs. His ſpirit was generous and noble, like that of the <hi>Eagle,</hi> which is not clamorous when it wants food. He ſtudied <hi>paſſive</hi> obedience as well as <hi>active;</hi> to be well-pleaſed with what God did, as well as to do what was well-pleaſing to God. He had a fit diſpoſition for the Croſs, which made that eaſy to him, which ſeemed into llerable to others. As he durſt not make men Lords of his faith, ſo neither of his happineſs, by doting on their <hi>ſmiles,</hi> or fearing their <hi>frowns;</hi> but as worldly men content themſelves with the world, without God; ſo he endeavoured to content himſelf with God, without the World. He had his preſent wants ſupplied, by ordinary or extraordinary means, and therefore conceived lit his duty to truſt God for the future: He knew he had more of the creature than he deſerved, and therefore was not: anxious about having more. He was much taken up about the weighty things of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity and therefore little concerned about theſe lower things.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55769:21"/>
               <p>He had many generous and noble diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but no one appeared more illuſtrious, and viſible in him,<note place="margin">His zeal for God.</note> after his converſion, than zeal for his Maſters ſervice; and the good of Souls. Oh! what a rare and excellent <hi>Quality</hi> is a publick Spirit for God? And how much was this holy man inveſted herewith? How little did his flamin zeal care to live, when the honour of his great Lord, ſeemed to bleed, and die? What a meek and patient Spirit had he, as to injury done unto himſelf? and yet how impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and zealous was he as to injury done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Lord? How modeſt and backward was he in his own cauſe? and yet how magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and forward in the cauſe of God? How little was it in the power of the greateſt men, to frown him out of duty, or flatter him into Sin? What a maſculine courage had he, with a fixed reſolution not to diſpleaſe God, to pleaſe men? Yea, how much vigor and ſtrength did his zeal gain by oppoſition? He ſeemed indeed naturally to have a Heroick ſpirit: But how much did Grace transform this natural quality into a Divine zeal? How much of divine flame, and how little of wildfire or carnal wrath was there in his zele?</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:55769:22"/>
               <p>Notwithſtanding his ardent zeal for God, yet was he of a very peaceable and quiet ſpirit.<note place="margin">His Catholick Charity.</note> He did not, <hi>Salamander-like,</hi> delight to live in the fire of contention; but was of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting healing ſpirit: He was not only a <hi>Patient,</hi> but alſo an <hi>Agent</hi> in ſeeking after peace: He judged our Church diviſions one of our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt plagues; He had a Catholick univerſal charity, and love for all: and albeit he hated the vices of wicked men, yet he loved their perſons. But he had a particular affection for all Saints, and that as Saints; making their <hi>graces,</hi> not their <hi>opinions,</hi> the meaſure of his love. His ſpirit and principles were ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as that he deſired to avoid all needleſs diſputes, that might breed ſtrife: But when he was called to diſpute, or confer with thoſe of different judgements, he evidenced much modeſty, and meekneſs; arguing not for glory, and victory, but to inquire into truth: Wherein he affirmed nothing, but what he endeavoured to prove out of the Scriptures: And when he could not fully comply with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens perſwaſions, yet he would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his own on them, as the rule of their faith or communion.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:55769:22"/>
               <p>And although he could <hi>forbear,</hi> and <hi>bear</hi> with all for their good, yet could he not bear with ſin in any;<note place="margin">His dexterity in Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs.</note> but was a ſevere <hi>Admonitor,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover</hi> thereof. Yea, his very preſence was a powerful and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive Admonition to ſuch as he reproved; for there was ſo much <hi>gravity</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> mixed in his countenance, that one word from him would oft effect more, then many from ſome others: Eſpecially, by his holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, exemplifying what he urged on others from the word of God, he much convinced ſuch as were defective, and ſubdued their wills to the will of God. I my ſelf once heard him, in the preſence of ſeveral Miniſters, ſharply reproving the ſin of Miniſters, in miſpending their time, whiles together, in <hi>frothy,</hi> or <hi>unprofitable conference:</hi> Which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof he managed with ſo much <hi>majeſty,</hi> and yet with ſo much humility, and ſubmiſſion; confirming all that he preſſed from the word of God, that, I muſt confeſs, I could not but conclude, that there was much of God, in his ſo ſeaſonable Admonition and Reproof.</p>
               <p>Neither did his <hi>ſeverity</hi> extend to the ſins of others only,<note place="margin">His vigilance and heart examens.</note> but alſo to his own: He was a curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of his own ſpirit, its
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55769:23"/>
                  <hi>ends, intentions, inclinations, motions, riſings,</hi> and <hi>fallings,</hi> as to Sin or Grace. He always kept a vigilant eye on his heart, and every night made particular reflexions on the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the day paſt, with a ſtrict examen, how it had been ſpent; what his converſation had been towards others; and how he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himſelf in his private duties towards God. He examined not only what he had done, but alſo from what principles he had done it; and thus by the knowledge of what he had done, he came the better to know, what he was to do; by ſtuddying well the book of his own heart, and life he became a good <hi>ſtudent,</hi> and <hi>proficient</hi> in the myſtery of godlineſs, and of ſin. He was a man of great obſervation, and of nothing more than of his own ſpirit its various viciſſitudes, turnings, and windings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus he came to have an intimate and deep acquaintance with his own heart; and an experimental ſenſe of the holy ſpirits working in him; Hence alſo he came to know, what ſins he had to confeſs, and humble himſelf for; what mercies to bleſs God, or petition for, what burdens to grone under. At ſome times he found himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great deadneſſes and diſtractions; at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times under ſweet inſpiration of the holy Spirit, and enlargements; Sometimes he ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55769:23"/>under ſinking deſpondences, black unbelief, and haſe fears; at other times, he was on the wing of faith, and full of courage.</p>
               <p>He had his ſtated times for private and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily duties: Faith and prayr were his chief refuſe in his troubles.<note place="margin">His private duties.</note> And, indeed, he ſeemed to drive a great trade with Heaven, by prayer; wherein he was very powerful and prevalent; He had a very ſtrngling, wreſtling ſpirit in Prayer; bottomed on a deep ſenſe of his own need, large deſires, and lively workings of faith. What ſtrength he gained by prayer, he loſt not by neglects after prayer, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for God. His Spirit ſeemed unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in duties, till he had met with God, or ſomething from God. Sometimes he was dull and indiſpoſed in the beginning of a duty; but before he came off, he oft found great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances; when he found weakneſſes, the Lord gave in unexpected ſupplies of ſtrength; when he was caſt down under any perplexing diſturbing fears, or difficulties from within or without, he had recourſe to his Bible, and thence received frequently ſuch ſweet and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging promiſes, ſet home by the ſpirit of God; as afforded abundance of refreſhing relief to him.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:55769:24"/>
               <p>His <hi>Family Exerciſes</hi> and Diſcipline de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a particular Remark. He gave no <hi>Toleration</hi> to any known ſin,<note place="margin">His Family Diſcipline.</note> or omiſſion of Duty: He was very diligent in preventing, or repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Prophanation of the Lords day, even to idle words: Neither was he leſs careful for the pious Education, and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe under his domeſtick charge. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning and evening, for the moſt part, he read, and expounded a part of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, ſung a Pſalm, and prayed with them. Every Friday night he examined their profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Aſſemblies leſſer Catechiſme, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining ſome part thereof to them. Every Lords day at night (beſides other Duties) he repeated the ſubſtance of what was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that day in the Sermons Preached: And after ſuch Exerciſes he examined his Servants, and ſuch Children as were capable, what they remembred; not ſuffering any to live under his Charge, who would not give account of their Faith. When he did not read a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, his courſe was to examine and inſtruct his Servants, concerning the Fundamentals of Religion, which was a great means for the improving their knowledge. Beſides his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Retirements, and Family-duties, he had his ſet times every day, to ſpend with his Wife in private prayer.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:55769:24"/>
               <p>Neither was this his religious care for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing Souls confined onely to his Family,<note place="margin">His holy Conſerence.</note> but extended unto others. He was inveſted with a ſingular Giſt of <hi>Perſonal Conference,</hi> which Talent he employed for the good of Souls; being ready to <hi>take,</hi> yea, to <hi>ſeek</hi> all conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent opportun ties to treat with them, about their eternal ſtate. He was much in preſſing men to Holineſs: He was wont to propoſe queſtions to thoſe he converſed with, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the like of them; which the Lord made very ſucceſsful He eſteemed it no ſmall burden to be caſt on any ſociety, where his time was ſpent in unprofitable diſcourſe; and when he was caſt on ſuch, his ordinary practice was, to put a ſtop to ſuch unedifying conference, by ſpiritual <hi>divertiſement,</hi> or turning it to ſome holy diſcourſe. When he intended to viſit any Chriſtian Family, his method was, firſt to call his Wife and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they might joyn with him in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for a bleſſing on his intended undertake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and being greatly ſenſible of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that are acquired by perſonal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, he gave thoſe of his hearers, whom he judged moſt judicious, divers directions for the right management thereof, on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55769:25"/>
               <p>He had a great <hi>Tenderneſs,</hi> and regard to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as were ſick: When he underſtood of their ſickneſs,<note place="margin">His Viſitation of the Sick.</note> he waited not till he was invited, neither did he rudely intrude where he might not be welcome; but firſt employed a Friend, to ſhew his willingneſs; and then where he might be received, he fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to viſit them, and to adminſter ſuch ſpiritual advice, as he conceiv'd moſt proper for the ſtate of their Souls. And to thoſe who wanted a competent ſupply of conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, he imparted not only of his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but alſo temporal Gifts, according to what God had bleſſed him with. He failed not to pray with them before his departure, nor to ſpare any labour, or trouble, in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this Chriſtian Office.</p>
               <p>As for other more extenſive parts of his <hi>Miniſterial Gifts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Miniſterial Gifts and Labours.</note> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> they were alſo very remarkable. His Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ſolid and practical; he had a great <hi>Pathos,</hi> and vehemence in ſetting home Truths on Conſcience: His Sermons were full of <hi>plainnſs,</hi> and yet clothed with a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Majeſty:</hi> His words were familiar, and yet very efficacious: He dwelt much on <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening</hi> Truths; ſuch as might pierce and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55769:25"/>ſting the Conſciences of ſecure ſinners; and yet to ſuch as needed <hi>Conſolation,</hi> he was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Barnabas,</hi> full of ſweetneſs. He had much of Divine <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> as well in the compoſing, as in the hearing of Sermons: He oft ſaid, that uſually his Sermons were given him on his knees: His practice was, when he had pitcht on a Text, to apply himſelf to Prayer; and whilſt he was on that duty, he oft had the Heads of his Diſcourſe give in unto him. As for his <hi>enlargements</hi> he was never barren; having a memory to treaſure up all that he read, and an Elocution apt to deliver what he had treaſured up, on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Thoſe who knew him, much admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how he could preach ſo oft, and yet ſo well. He was likewiſe endued with a large gift of prayer. which he alwayes expreſſed in Scriptural language, wherein he ſeemed to have much communion with God.</p>
               <p>In brief, he was one of Divine <hi>Lights</hi> and <hi>Heats</hi> for God. His zeal in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the ways of God,<note place="margin">A Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maris of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</note> was fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and ardent: He was affable in his Speech, ſerious and grave in his Carriage, invincible in his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Charitable to ſuch as differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from in perſuaſions, ſo long as he ſaw their deſign was to promote Godlineſs; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55769:26"/>in the uſe of the Creature, Frugal in the husbanding of his time, ſpending his ſpare hours in walking, meditating. Praying, or converſing with Chriſtians about Soul-affairs. And indeed, he was of ſo holy a diſpoſition, and heavenly temper, as that all good Men who knew him, reverenced him. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, his greateſt ambition ſeemed this, to act and ſuffer ſomewhat more then ordinary for God; that ſo he might, by a ſingular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary converſation, ſilence the reproaches of ungodly men, and give check to the Pride, Formality, Vanity and Carnality of too many Profeſſors in theſe wanton days, which he ſadly bewailed, as ſad prognoſticks of great Deſolations: Only, he hoped there were ſome, and the Lord would raiſe up more young Converts, who ſhould be furniſhed with Spirits, and converſations for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of Chriſts Kingdom. But more of his Spirit, Fears, and hopes, will appear, in, and by his following Letters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb facs="tcp:55769:26"/>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>Penryn Octob. <hi>5. 1669.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear and Reſpected Brother.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I May tell you ſad ſtories of my heart; O! how unbelieving, fearful, and faint found I it, on thoſe ſhort views I took of it: But that God, on whom my ſcandalous heart hath raiſed ſo many falſe ſtories heretofore, and then gave my fears the lie; and yet continue I untoucht, and undiſturbed to this hour. I do caſt my ſelf on the diſpoſing hand of God, to live or die in my liberty, according to his pleaſure; When I go forth, not expecting to ſee my Family again, and my frequent eſcapes, fill me with pleaſing admirations of love, that (through Grace) I return trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing in his goodneſs. How long this liberty may be indulged, I know not; but I know he will be a good God when he ſeizeth our freedom in the Goſpel: and it will be the Rod of a Father, and may tend to our increaſe &amp; ſettlement. I have had one very ſtrange raiſing from the Grave ſince I ſaw you; the circumſtances whereof compelled me,
<pb facs="tcp:55769:27"/>and others to own a very viſible finger of God: But a Narrative of this would be too tedious; I deſire you would be importunate with God, that I might eye the approaching Glory, and the return of that great Shepheard, and might feed in hope, ſingly aiming at the Lords bleſſed Intereſt, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with my own greateſt decreaſes, might that be increaſed and enlarged. Gods waterings and bleſſigs muſt give life and fruit to all our poor and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive labourings. O! Beg that theſe may be eminently with me; poor <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> I think is near heavy ſtrokes for her barrenneſs, ſenſuality, and enmity againſt the power of holineſs: the Lord grant this may not come as a ſnare on you and me; but that we may be ſober and watchful unto Prayer. The gracious Lord, who dwelt in the buſh, be with you, to teach, ſtrengthen and warn you, that in his hand you may be ſerviceable and glorious; In him I am, and ever ſhall be,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your unfeigned friend, yet unworthy ſervant, <hi>T. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55769:27"/>
                  <head>Penryn Jan. 12. 1669.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Should rejoyce to hear how God is dealing with your inward man, and what meaſures of ſucceſs you are crowned with in your labours of the Goſpel, and intereſt of the Son of God in the world. We may juſtly gueſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t God will do with us in the Land, by his breathings with his truths. I deſire with much earneſtneſs to know (ſeeing you have ſo many advantages beyond us in theſe poor corners) how the Spirits of Profeſſors ſtand qualify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo far as a conjecture may be made, by the viſible tenure of their carriages. I generally find a very ſecure, earthly, laizy frame hath ſeized thoſe among whom I occaſionally fall abroad: I hope better things with you; and that a more engaging relliſh, and taſte of God &amp; Glory, is fallen on their hearts; and a more refined pure lip, ſeconded by more humble, ſelf-denying conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before the world. O! What a bleſſed <hi>Omen</hi> would this be, that God
<pb facs="tcp:55769:28"/>is on healing tearms of Grace with <hi>England;</hi> I muſt confeſs in the place where I now labour God is travelling forth with a meaſure of the greatneſs of his might: Some moſt ſtubborn and obſtinate wretches attend the means, and our meetings grow; the Spirit of Jeſus hath made ſome to fall under him, and our hopes of greater things are increaſing; if the Lord for our unfruitful walkings blaſt not all. My Dear Brother; I need not tell you how ſweet it is to be tabernacling in Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> by cloſe believing. Meditation, to ſee your Lord and mine; and on thoſe views to rejoyce with joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory: and by the ſtme alſo to mourn over unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with bitterneſs, as for an only Son. Your received anointings lead me, and keep you there: Only I muſt tell you, Sermons much watered in the Cloſet, and ſteep'd in fervent Prayer, will ordinarily prove moſt quickening to the dead, and conſolating to the Saints; and a heart dropt upon by ſuch views, will lay a more then uſual tincture of Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mouth which will have a choice influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in a Teachers treating with Souls. I muſt commit you to <hi>Iſraels</hi> Keeper, in whom you may repute me,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your unfeigned well-wiſhing friend, and engaged Brother, <hi>T. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:55769:28"/>
                  <head>Jan. 28. 1669.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I See you have taken up a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary care for me; the ground of which I ſuppoſe, is, ſomewhat of God you conjecture is upon me: In which, I beg the Lord you may not be miſtaken. If I ſhould confeſs the truth to my boſom Brother, my Heart is ſuch a confuſed diſorder'd piece, its Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and ends lying ſo viel'd and hidden from my ſelf, that moſt frequently I am mine own ſtranger; I know not who, or what I am, whether God or ſelf ſwayes me. Only this ſtayes me, that were the eye of my heart levelled as directly, and in as much ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at the glory of God in Chriſt, as I would have it be in my greateſt ſtrangeneſs to him and my ſelf, I think I ſhould be ſincere. This therefore being much my ſtate, I may admire at the touch of Gods Finger on your heart, to turn it to ſuch a worm. I had no ſooner the Letter, but I ſaw much of God by it; and in ſuch providences, (through the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer) I deſire to hold ſome communion with him. I ſhall hint at a footſtep of the bleſſed walks of God to me, ſo far as your Lines may require. Seven or eight years ſince, I found amongſt the writings of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed friend, two Bonds belonging to a
<pb facs="tcp:55769:29"/>poor Ophan; on the finding of which, I ſent word to the Orphan, of them, who came to the Houſe where I dwelt, and gave order that one of her Debtors ſhould be ſued, for the calling in her Money. Accordingly that Bond was ſent to a Lawyer, and the Debtor ſued; But it being out of the way of my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to attend ſuch a buſineſs, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Orphan I ſhould not follow that affair, but leave it to a Kinſman of hers to manage it; and accordingly regarded it no further; he promiſing to ſhew all fidelity for the bringing in from the Debtor, the Money to the Orphan. In proceſs of time, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard of the buſineſs, either from the Orphan or her Kinſman, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all matters were regularly managed, and in equity between them. As I was alone in my impriſonment, I had a thought that ſtuck upon me. I muſt needs enquire what iſſue of the Orphans affair, in her Kinſmans hand had attained; and on an inquiry, found out that the Orphan was abuſed, and damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied 14 <hi>l.</hi> by this Kinſman, who yet had ſo ſaved himſelf, that no Juſtice could be gaind againſt him. On which I was under many diſputes with my ſelf, whether I were not obliged to take care the Orphan might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. I did propoſe the caſe, but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the Negative. However, becauſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55769:29"/>I entruſted it in his hand, I could not ſo clearly diſcharge my ſelf; and therefore lately borrowed the money, and paid it to the Orphan; reſolving, notwithſtanding my preſent condition, rather to be the ſufferer my ſelf, then that the fatherleſs Child, by the others injuſtice, ſhould be injured; and was determined to eye the Lord for a way to diſcharge that money ſo borrowed. Within a very little time I had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed the 14. <hi>l.</hi> yours came; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a little ſeaſon from another; and now you write me of more, which makes up the ſum. I have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what moved under the graciouſneſs of God: the Lord make me fruitful in my ſeaſonable improvement of this diſpenſation. I ſhould be very glad, might I ſee you at <hi>Crediton</hi> in my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up to the Aſſizes: Many things I have to ſay, which I muſt ſilence, till God open a door for a more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory converſe. You are minded by us here, and I deſire to live on your thoughts, when neareſt God.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>I am yours in unfeignedneſs,</hi> T. T.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:55769:30"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>May</hi> 11. 1670.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOurs of the <hi>16th.</hi> of April, I received not till the <hi>7th.</hi> inſtant. Your long ſilence I confeſs much ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed me: but now in your lines, and the reaſon by them given me of the ſuſpence in thoſe paper-enter courſes, I rejoyce. Since my laſt lines to you, according to my engagement by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance; I had an opportunity to ſpend ſome time with your friends at <hi>Crediton, Chimly,</hi> and <hi>Southmoulton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and am ſorry where there is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſo encouraging an harveſt, ſo little ſtomack, and ſpirit is found in adjacent Labourers. It hath been long my thought, that God hath yet a great controverſie with the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming (though the beſt) part of the Engliſh Miniſtry; among whom how few are there who naturally care for the ſtate of the poor periſhing Countrey; and what their hands find
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55769:30"/>to do, <hi>do it with their might?</hi> This with that levity of Spirit, unholineſs of Lip, Reigning Selfiſhneſs, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindedneſs, Formality, Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs in Worſhip, Security, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> viſible upon the profeſſing body, doth as apparently and dangerouſly threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>England,</hi> as the more branded D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries. I could heartily wiſh (had the wiſe Lord ſeen it fit) your ſtation had been fixed in your native Soil, that you might be to the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Brethren, and profeſſing Saints; and alſo ready at hand to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thoſe poor corners, which ſeem to cry as the <hi>Macedonian</hi> in the viſion, <hi>Come over and help us.</hi> But you know your proper gift, and I preſume will carefully ſtudy and anſwer your calls. I did contract friendſhip in that jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, with Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> whom I find of another Spirit, in whoſe ſociety my Soul was refreſhed: And Mr. <hi>Flavel</hi> of <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> I find a well tempered Man; whom elſe I met with to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in, of my Brethren I ſcarce know
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55769:31"/>any. The times are now very black, and clouds are gathering in every quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; what the iſſue of our ſtorms may be, a little time will much indicate, I wiſh I could ſay, <hi>Nubecula cito tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibit;</hi> To give you my fears, I think this nothing to what muſt enſue: I have been long waiting for this; and do conſidently believe this not the deareſt teſtimony that muſt be given to Goſpel-truths, and Duties. A national overwhelming cluſter of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere judgments, I am ſore afraid, is at the door, ſharper then what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, for ſome ſcores of years we have felt: though I hope there will be a larger meaſure of God to ſanctifie them, for the reforming of his own, and converting the Rebels, then ever we yet experienced. This I confeſs, is ſome ſtay to me, under what I am enforced to believe. I have often begged, if the Lord ſees I am like to prove a diſhonour to his Intereſt, he would firſt ſhut me up in the duſt. <hi>Dear Brother,</hi> Pray for me, that I may
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55769:31"/>do my work according to my convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, humbly and with ſucceſs; and that after my teachings of others, and ſmall ſufferings, I may not be a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Light, Love, and Life, by which the Saints are quickned, and ſo at laſt a Caſtaway. The Lord make you uſeful, and keep up your courage, and grant you a deliverance from rude and unreaſonable men, which, with deſires of the like cequeſts from you on my behalf, will be now all,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From your moſt affectionate and engaged Brother in the Faith.</hi> T. T.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55769:32"/>
                  <head>Penryn, September <hi>16. 1670.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AT this Aſſize at <hi>Exon</hi> I was call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to my Trial, but no perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor appearing to give evidence againſt me; my jury acquitted me, and a Verdict of <hi>not guilty</hi> was returned. <hi>George Smith,</hi> the Deputy major of <hi>Torrington,</hi> when the Conventicle was ſurprized (and the grand Enemy in this affair) was at Lent Aſſize at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending: but the Trial being put off; by this Aſſize God diſabled him for ſuch a journey, he having received in a drunken voyage, a fall from his Horſe; by which his ſhoulder-bone is diſlocated, and he rendred unable to dreſs or undreſs himſelf; and ſo like to abide to the day of his death. His Wife alſo (that violent Woman) died of a Timpany, a fearful ſpectacle to all beholders; ſhe departed hence the night of that Lords day in which I exerciſed at <hi>Torrington,</hi> in my journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55769:32"/>now to my home. I ſuppoſe you heard of the bad end of another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor there, one <hi>Denys, Smith,</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law, who ſo much rejoyced when our meeting was broken up, affirming, the ſurprizal of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle did him more good, and more rejoyced him then all his loſſes did ſadden him: his Wife alſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly belch'd forth theſe words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me, hang the Rogue; hang him at the Sign-poſt, or next Tree, and never ſend him to <hi>Exon:</hi> This poor wretch did hang himſelf in his own Study, and thereby his Eſtate is forfeited to the Town. Many much take notice, how ſignally Gods hand hath been againſt them ſince that Meeting. There are a very precious handful at <hi>Chinely, Southmoulton,</hi> and adjacent parts, who gladly receive the word: their ready ſubmiſſion to the truth in my former journey, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged my heart to viſit them again, and hope our ſeeing each other hath not been in vain: Your memory is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55769:33"/>dear to ſundry of them, and your ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings there. I wiſh they might again ſee you. A fruitful heavenly lip to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove truths imparted, by correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding preſſing conferences, is much wanting among us: I pray beg it for me, and your other Brethren, now labouring My complaint will not Crucifie my unbelief, pride and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; pray labour for me with God, with whom I leave you, and am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your much obliged Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lord. <hi>T. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55769:33"/>
                  <head>Penryn, October <hi>7. 1670.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am a Sympathizer with you in dear Mr. <hi>R's</hi> loſs of ſo choice a mate; but ſuppoſe his ſo exemplary living on God, will do much to quiet him in the loſs of the beſt injoyment not everlaſting; and the ground of hope ſhe is ſafely houſ'd from the ſtorms we feel and fear, will I believe, and do more ſweetly reconcile him to this ungrateful and fleſh-diſguſting ſtroke. As for what God ſpeaks to you in this providence, I think its plain, <hi>viz. That you more effectually daily dye to what is not God and Spirit; and that you enure your Soul to more deep and fixed thoughts of your own diſſolution.</hi> I hear many very precious ones have been lately, at <hi>London</hi> (through a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant diſtemper in the Bowels) called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome; the Lord more fully warn them who ſurvive, and us; alſo of thoſe black and tempting days which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55769:34"/>probably are near us. My thoughts have been much of late ſetled, I know not how, on a converſing with the ſtate of departed Saints, Martyr'd for the teſtimony of Jeſus. I have obſerved in ſpecial two paſſages in Mr. <hi>Foxes Acts,</hi> &amp;c. The one of Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> the Protomartyr in <hi>Marys</hi> Reign; who in his Priſon had this paſſage to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Mr. <hi>Foxes</hi> book, then in bonds with him, <hi>Thou</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſhalt live to ſee the alteration of this Religion, and the Goſpel freely preached again: and therefore have me commended to my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as well in</hi> Exile <hi>as others; and bid them be circumſpect in diſplacing the Papiſts, and putting good Miniſters into Churches, or elſe their end will be worſe then ours.</hi> The Printer accordingly lived, but what remains for us who have ſhamefully ſlighted his counſel, time will evidence. The other is from Mr. <hi>Holland,</hi> who thus beſpeaks <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> after his ſentence; <hi>This I dare be bold in God to ſpeak (which by his Spirit I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> moved to ſay) that God will ſhorten
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55769:34"/>our hand of cruelty; that for a time you ſhall not moleſt his Church; and this ſhall you in ſhort time well perceive</hi> (my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) <hi>to be moſt true; for after this day in this place, there ſhall not be any, by him put to the tryal of Fire and Faggot.</hi> After which there was not one burned in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> I principally conſider that expreſſion, <hi>That for a time they ſhould not moleſt his Church.</hi> The Lord prepare me for a ſuffering day, and if fair weather ſucceeds, we ſhall be more watchful in its improvement. As for our condition 'tis full of threats and trouble; Warrants are granted for the levying of 220 <hi>l.</hi> on me; yet God hath kept them off; but I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting daily to be ſtripp'd of all. Our meeting place is taken from us, through their threatnings on our Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord: we now meet at my houſe, and once each Lords-day above the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; but very few are free to attend, unleſs with four. I am alſo threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be perſecuted on the corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Law; ſo that I am conſtantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55769:35"/>an impriſonment: but I ſhall endeavour to turn into the ſtrong hold, as a Priſoner of hope. I ſhould very gladly underſtand more particularly, how it is with you in this troubleſome and ſickly time; however, the Lord clear up your intereſt, and grant you an open door; if called hence into his preſence with exceeding joy. I ſhall commit you to God, beſeeching him to guid and uſe you, and to preſerve you blameleſs to his Kingdom.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>I am yours moſt unfeignedly.</hi> T. T.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:55769:35"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>P. 4. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> others. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>dele</hi> of them. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> about. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>for</hi> converſion <hi>r.</hi> converſation. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 24 <hi>for</hi> convenant <hi>r.</hi> convert. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> ond <hi>r.</hi> and. <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>for</hi> hoth <hi>r.</hi> hath. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>dele</hi> you know I have. <hi>p.</hi> 36. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> related. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>after</hi> in <hi>add</hi> underſtanding. <hi>p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> refuſe <hi>r.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge. <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>after</hi> him <hi>r.</hi> in. <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> ſome <hi>r.</hi> ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
